The Banana Protocol

NOTE! This is all preliminary and is more an exercise in semiconscious protocol design than anything else. Do not believe this document. This sentence is lying. So there.

Banana tokens

At the lowest layer, the wire transport takes the form of Tokens. These all take the shape of header/type-byte/body, where the type byte has its high bit set, to distinguish it from the header bytes that precede it. Some tokens have bodies, some do not, and the length of all bodies are determined by data in the header. The bodies are composed of arbitrary bytes. For most tokens, the header is a base-128 number, but for some it may be a UTF-7 encoded string. (?? maybe just strict ASCII. the high bit of all bytes in the header must be zero). The maximum legal header length is 64 bytes, so tokens which treat it as a number have a maximum value of 2**(64*7)-1.

Tokens are described below as [header-TOKEN-body], where either header or body may be empty. For example, [len-LIST-empty] indicates that the length is put into the header, LIST is the token being used, and the body is empty.

The possible Token types are:

0x80: LIST (old): [len-LIST-empty]

This token marks the beginning of a list with LEN elements. It acts as the open parenthesis, and the matching close parenthesis is implicit, based upon the length of the list. It will be followed by LEN things, which may be tokens like INTs or STRINGS, or which may be sublists. Banana keeps a list stack to handle nested sublists.

This token (and the notion of length-prefixed lists in general) is from oldbanana. In newbanana it is only used during the initial dialect negotiation (so that oldbanana peers can be detected). Newbanana requires that LIST(old) tokens be followed exclusively by strings and have a rather limited allowable length (say, 640 dialects long).

0x81: INT: [value-INT-empty]

This token defines a single positive integer. The protocol defines its range as [0, 2**31), so the largest legal value is 2**31-1. The recipient is responsible for choosing an appropriate local type to hold the number. For Python, if the value represented by the incoming base-128 digits grows larger than a regular Python IntType can accomodate, the receiving system will use a LongType or a BigNum as necessary.

Anything larger than this range must be sent with a LONGINT token instead.

(oldbanana compatibility note: a python implementation can accept anything in the range [0, 2**448), limited by the 64-byte maximum header size).

The range was chosen to allow INT values to always fit in C's s_int32_t type, so an implementation that doesn't have a useful bignum type can simply reject LONGINT tokens.

0x82: STRING [len-STRING-chars]

This token defines a string. To be precise, it defines a sequence of bytes. The length is a base-128-encoded integer. The type byte is followed by LEN bytes of data which make up the string. LEN is required to be shorter than 640k: this is intended to reduce the amount of memory that can be consumed on the receiving end before user code gets to decide whether to accept the data or not.

0x83: NEG: [value-NEG-empty]

This token defines a negative integer. It is identical to the INT tag except that the results are negated before storage. The range is defined as [-2**31, 0), again to make an implementation using s_int32_t easier. Any numbers smaller (more negative) than this range must be sent with a LONGNEG token.

Implementations should be tolerant when receiving a negative zero and turn it into a 0, even though they should not send such things.

Note that NEG can represent a number (-2**31) whose absolute value (2**31) is one larger than the greatest number that INT can represent (2**31-1).

0x84: FLOAT [empty-FLOAT-value]

This token defines a floating-point number. There is no header, and the type byte is followed by 8 bytes which are a 64-bit IEEE double, as defined by struct.pack("!d", num).

0x85: OLDLONGINT: [value-OLDLONGINT-empty]

0x86: OLDLONGNEG: [value-OLDLONGNEG-empty]

These were used by oldbanana to represent large numbers. Their size was limited by the number of bytes in the header (max 64), so they can represent [0, 2**448).

0x87: VOCAB: [index-VOCAB-empty]

This defines a tokenized string. Banana keeps a mapping of common strings, each one is assigned a small integer. These strings can be sent compressed as a two-byte (index, VOCAB) sequence. They are delivered to Jelly as plain strings with no indication that they were compressed for transit.

The strings in this mapping are populated by the sender when it sends a special vocab OPEN sequence. The intention is that this mapping will be sent just once when the connection is first established, but a sufficiently ambituous sender could use this to implement adaptive forward compression.

0x88: OPEN: [[num]-OPEN-empty]

0x89: CLOSE: [[num]-CLOSE-empty]

These tokens are the newbanana parenthesis markers. They carry an optional number in their header: if present, the number counts the appearance of OPEN tokens in the stream, starting at 0 for the first OPEN used for a given connection and incrementing by 1 for each subsequent OPEN. The matching CLOSE token must contain an identical number. These numbers are solely for debugging and may be omitted. They may be removed from the protocol once development has been completed.

In contrast to oldbanana (with the LIST token), newbanana does not use length-prefixed lists. Instead it relies upon the Banana layer to track OPEN/CLOSE tokens.

The token which follows an OPEN marker must be a string: either a STRING token or a VOCAB token. This string indicates what kind of new sub-expression is being started.

0x8A: ABORT: [[num]-ABORT-empty]

This token indicates that something has gone wrong on the sender side, and that the resulting object must not be handed upwards in the unslicer stack. It may be impossible or inconvenient for the sender to stop sending the tokens associated with the unfortunate object, so the receiver must be prepared to silently drop all further tokens up to the matching STOP marker.

The number, if present, will be the same one used by the OPEN token.

0x8B: LONGINT: [len-LONGINT-bytes]

0x8C: LONGNEG: [len-LONGNEG-bytes]

These are processed like STRING tokens, but the bytes form a base-256 encoded number, most-significant-byte first (note that this may require several passes and some intermediate storage). The size is (barely) limited by the length field, so the theoretical range is [0, 2**(2**(64*7)-1)-1), but the receiver can impose whatever length limit they wish.

LONGNEG is handled exactly like LONGINT but the number is negated first.

TODO: Add TRUE, FALSE, and NONE tokens.

Object graph serialization

When serializing an object, it is useful to view it as a directed graph. The root object is the one you start with, any objects it refers to are children of that root. Those children may point back to other objects that have already been serialized, or which will be serialized later.

Banana, like pickle and other serialization schemes, does a depth-first traversal of this graph. Serialization is begun on each node before going down into the child nodes. Banana tracks previously-handled nodes and replaces them with numbered reference tokens to break loops in the graph.

Banana Slices

A Banana Slicer is responsible for serializing a single user object: it slices that object into a series of Banana tokens. On the receiving end, there is a corresponding Banana Unslicer which accepts the incoming tokens and re-creates the user object. There are different kinds of Slicers and Unslicers for lists, tuples, dictionaries, and instances. Classes can provide their own Slicers if they want more control over the serialization process.

The Banana Stack

The serialization context is stored in a Banana object (names are still being decided). This holds a stack of Banana Slicers, one per object currently being serialized (i.e. one per node in the path from the root object to the object currently being serialized).

For example, suppose a class instance is being serialized, and this class chose to use a dictionary to hold its instance state. That dictionary holds a list of numbers in one of its values. The Banana Stack would hold the root slicer, an InstanceSlicer, a DictSlicer, and finally a ListSlicer.

(note: it might be possible to move the functionality of the Banana object entirely into the root slice (root slicer?)).

Upon unserialization, the Unbanana object holds this context. A stack of Unslicer objects handle incoming tokens. The Unbanana is responsible for tracking OPEN and CLOSE tokens, making sure a failure in an Unslicer doesn't cause a loss of synchronization. Unslicer methods may raise exceptions: these are caught by the Unbanana and cause the object currently being unserialized to fail: its parent gets a UnbananaFailure instead of the dict or list or instance that it would normally have received.

The stack is used to determine three things:

Whether to allow a given child to be serialized: the Taster function
How to handle a child object: which Slicer should be used
How to track object references, to break cycles in the object graph

The default case puts a Parent slice at the bottom of the stack. This can also be interpreted as a root object, if you imagine that any given user object being serialized is somehow a child of the overall serialization context. In PB, for example, the root object would be related to the connection.

In addition, the stack can be queried to find out what path leads from the root object to the one currently being serialized. If something goes wrong in the serialization process (an exception is thrown), this path can make it much easier to find out when the trouble happened, as opposed to merely where. Knowing which method of your FooObject failed during serialization isn't very useful when you have 500 of them inside your data structure and you need to know whether it was bar.thisfoo or bar.thatfoo which caused the problem. To this end, each Slicer has a .describe method which is supposed to return a short string that explains how to get to the child node currently being processed. When an error occurs, these strings are concatenated together and put into the failure object.

The Parent slice is meant to provide the default behavior for the stack. The default class currently does the following:

Allow all objects to be serialzed: .taster is empty.
Use the BananaRegistry mapping from object types to Slicer classes.
Record object references in a dict inside the parent slice.

TODO: The idea is to let other serialization contexts to other things. The tokens should probably go to the parent slice for handling: turning into bytes and sending over a wire, saving to a file, etc. Having the whole stack participate in the Tasting process means that objects can put restrictions on what is sent on their behalf: objects could refuse to let certain classes be sent as part of their instance state.

Bananaing

Serialization starts with the Parent Slicer being asked to serialize the given object. The Parent gives the object to Banana. Banana starts by walking the stack (which, of course, has only the Parent on it at that point), calling the .taste method for each Slicer there. If any of them have a problem with the object being serialized, they express it by raising an exception (TODO: which one? InsecureBanana?).

If the Taster stack passes the object, Banana's next job is to find a new Slicer to handle the object. It does this by walking the stack, calling .newSlicer on each slice. The first one that returns an object ends the search. In most cases, this is the Parent slice, which just looks up the type() of the object in the SlicerRegistry. A type which does not have a Slicer registered for it will cause an exception to be raised here.

The new Slicer is pushed on the the stack. It is then sent three methods in succession: .start, .slice, and .finish. start defaults to registering the object with setRefID and sending a appropriate OPEN token. slice is defined on a per-Slicer basis to send all the necessary tokens. finish sends the CLOSE token.

Banana keeps strict track of the nesting level. For safety, each OPEN gets a sequence number so it can be matched with its CLOSE token. If a Slicer's .close method fails to send the close token, very bad things will happen (in general, all further objects will become children of the one that didn't CLOSE properly). The sequence numbers are an attempt to minimize the damage.

Unbananaing

The Unbanana object has a corresponding stack of Banana Unslicer objects. Each one receives the tokens emitted by the matching Slicer on the sending side. The whole stack is used to determine new Unslicer objects, perform Tasting of incoming tokens, and manage object references.

OPEN tokens have a string (or short list of tokens.. see below) to indicate what kind of object is being started. This is looked up in the UnbananaRegistry just like object types are looked up in the BananaRegistry. The new Unslicer is pushed onto the stack.

ABORT tokens indicate that something went wrong on the sending side and that the current object is to be aborted. It causes the receiver to ignore all tokens until the CLOSE token which closes the current node. This is implemented by replacing the top-most slice with a DiscardUnslicer.

CLOSE tokens finish the current node. The slice will pass its completed object up to the childFinished method of its parent.

Open Index tokens

To be precise, OPEN tokens are followed by an arbitrary list of other tokens which are used to determine which UnslicerFactory should be invoked to create the new Unslicer. Basic Python types are designated with a simple string, like (OPEN list) or (OPEN dict), but instances are serialized with two strings (OPEN instance classname), and various exotic PB objects like method calls may involve a list of strings and numbers (OPEN call reqID objID methodname). The unbanana code works with the unslicer stack's designated opener object to apply constraints to these indexing tokens and finally obtain the new Unslicer when enough indexing tokens have been received.

The reason for assembling this list before creating the Unslicer (instead of using a generic InstanceUnslicer which switches behavior depending upon its first received token) is to support classes or PB methods which wish to push custom Unslicers to handle their deserialization process. For example, a class could push a StreamingFileUnslicer that accepts a series of string tokens and appends their contents to a file on disk. This Unslicer could reduce memory consumption (by only holding one chunk at a time) and update some kind of progress indicator as the data arrives. This particular feature was provided by the old StringPager utility, but custom Unslicers offer more flexibility and better efficiency (no additional round-trips).

(note: none of this affects the serialization side: those Slicers emit both their indexing tokens and their state tokens. It is only the receiving side where the index tokens are handled by a different piece of code than the content tokens).

In yet greater detail:

Each OPEN sequence is divided into an Index phase and a Contents phase. The first one (or two or three) tokens are the Index Tokens and the rest are the Content Tokens. The sequence ends with a CLOSE token.
Banana.inOpen is a boolean which indicates that we are in the Index Phase. It is set to True when the OPEN token is received and returns to False after the new Unslicer has been pushed.
Banana.opentype is a list of Index Tokens that are being accumulated. It is cleared each time .inOpen is set to True. The tuple form of opentype is passed to Slicer.doOpen, Constraint.checkOpentype, and used as a key in the RootSlicer.openRegistry dictionary. Each Unslicer type is indexed by an opentype tuple.

If .inOpen is True, each new token type will be passed (through Banana.getLimit and top.openerCheckToken) to the opener's .openerCheckToken method, along with the current opentype tuple. The opener gets to decide if the token is acceptable (possibly raising a BananaError exception), and may return a length limit (usually for strings). Note that the opener does not maintain state about what phase the decoding process is in, so it may want to condition its response upon the length of the opentype.

After each index token is complete, it is appended to .opentype, then the list is passed (through Banana.handleOpen, top.doOpen, and top.open) to the opener's .open method. This can either return an Unslicer (which will finish the index phase: all further tokens will be sent to the new Unslicer), return None (to continue the index phase), raise a Violation (which causes an UnbananaFailure to be passed to the current top unslicer), or raise another exception (which causes the connection to be abandoned).

Unslicer Lifecycle

Each Unslicer handles a single OPEN sequence, which starts with an OPEN token and ends with a CLOSE token (or an ABORT token).

Creation

Acceptance of the OPEN token simply sets a flag to indicate that we are in the Index Phase. (The OPEN token might not be accepted: it is submitted to checkToken for approval first, as described below). During the Index Phase, all tokens are appended to the current opentype list and handed as a tuple to the top-most Unslicer's doOpen method. This method can do one of the following things:

Return a new Unslicer object. It does this when there are enough index tokens to specify a new Unslicer. The new child is pushed on top of the Unslicer stack (Banana.receiveStack) and initialized by calling the start method described below. This ends the Index Phase.
Return None. This indicates that more index tokens are required. The Banana protocol object simply remains in the Index Phase and continues to accumulate index tokens.
Raise a Violation
Raise some other exception

When a new Unslicer object is pushed on the top of the stack, it has its .start method called, in which it has an opportunity to create whatever internal state is necessary to record the incoming content tokens. Each created object will have a separate Unslicer instance. (TODO: could optimize with singleton Unslicer objects, using start/finish methods to do cleanup). The start method can run normally, or raise a Violation exception, or some other exception.

This Unslicer is responsible for all incoming tokens until either 1: it pushes a new one on the stack, or 2: it receives a CLOSE token.

checkToken

Each token starts with a length sequence, up to 64 bytes which are turned into an integer. This is followed by a single type byte, distinguished from the length bytes by having the high bit set (the type byte is always 0x80 or greater). When the typebyte is received, the topmost Unslicer is asked about its suitability by calling the .checkToken method. (note that CLOSE and ABORT tokens are always legal, and are not submitted to checkToken). This method is expected to do one of the following:

Return an integer called sizelimit. If the token body is larger than sizelimit, the token will be rejected. This is used for STRING, LONGINT, and LONGNEG tokens.
Raise a Violation exception to reject the token. This will cause the remainder of the current OPEN sequence to be discarded (all tokens through the matching CLOSE token). Unslicers should raise this if their constraints will not accept the incoming object: for example a constraint which is expecting a series of integers can accept INT/NEG/LONGINT/LONGNEG tokens and reject OPEN/STRING/VOCAB/FLOAT tokens. The topmost Unslicer (the same one which raised Violation) will receive (through its .receiveChild method) an UnbananaFailure object which encapsulates the reason for the rejection
Raise some other exception

If the token sequence is in the index phase (i.e. it is just after an OPEN token and a new Unslicer has not yet been pushed), then instead of .checkToken the top unslicer is sent .openerCheckToken. This method behaves just like checkToken, but in addition to the type byte it is also given the opentype list (which is built out of all the index tokens received during this index phase).

receiveChild

If the type byte is accepted, and the size limit is obeyed, then the rest of the token is read and a finished (primitive) object is created: a string, number, boolean, or None. This object is handed to the topmost Unslicer's .receiveChild method, where again it is has a few options:

Run normally: if the object is acceptable, it should append or record it somehow.
Raise Violation, just like checkToken.
Raise some other exception
invoke self.abort, which does protocol.abandonUnslicer

If the child is handed an UnbananaFailure object, and it wishes to pass it upwards to its parent, then self.abort is the appropriate thing to do. Raising an exception will accomplish the same thing, but with a new UnbananaFailure that describes the exception raised here instead of the one raised by a child object. It is bad to both call abort and raise an exception.

Finishing

When the CLOSE token arrives, the Unslicer will have its .receiveClose method called. This is expected to do:

Return an object: this object is the finished result of the deserialization process. It will be passed to .receiveChild of the parent Unslicer.
Return a Deferred: this indicates that the object cannot be created yet (tuples that contain references to an enclosing tuple, for example). The Deferred will be fired (with the object) when it completes.
Raise Violation
Raise some other exception

After receiveClose has finished, the child is told to clean up by calling its .finish method. This can complete normally or raise a Violation, BananaError, or something else.

Then, the old top-most Unslicer is popped from the stack and discarded. Its parent is now the new top-most Unslicer, and the newly-unserialized object is given to it with the .receiveChild method. Note that this method is used to deliver both primitive objects (from raw tokens) and composite objects (from other Unslicers).

Error Handling

Schemas are enforced by Constraint objects which are given an opportunity to pass judgement on each incoming token. When they do not like something they are given, they respond by raising a Violation exception. The Violation exception is sometimes created with an argument that describes the reason for the rejection, but frequently it is just a bare exception. Most Violations are raised by the checkOpentype and checkObject methods of the various classes in schema.py.

Exceptions which occur in an Unslicer (whether Violations or something more serious) can be confined to a single sub-tree of the object graph. The object being deserialized (and all of its children) is abandoned, and all remaining tokens for that object are discarded. However, the parent object (to which the abandoned object would have been given) gets to decide what happens next: it can either fail itself, or absorb the failure (much like an exception handler can choose to re-raise the exception or eat it).

Confinable exceptions are wrapped in an UnbananaFailure object. The UnbananaFailure behaves like a regular twisted.python.failure.Failure object, except that it has an attribute named .where which indicate the object-graph pathname where the problem occurred. The UnbananaFailure is passed up the Unslicer stack in lieu of an actual object. Most Unslicers have code in their receiveChild methods to detect an UnbananaFailure and trigger an abort, which causes all further tokens of the sub-tree to be discarded. The connection is not dropped. Unslicers which partition their children's sub-graphs (like the PBRootUnslicer, for which each child is a separate operation) can simply ignore the UnbananaFailure, or respond to it by sending an error message to the other end.

Other exceptions may occur during deserialization. Unrecognized opentypes will probably cause a KeyError when the opener attempts to map them to an Unserializer class. Coding erors could cause unexpected exceptions. If these occur in the context of an Unslicer, they are wrapped in UnbananaFailures and handled just like Violations. The only difference is that non-Violations are always logged with log.err (including a traceback), whereas Violations are passed through the Banana.logViolation method which may or may not log it (and will probably not include a traceback).

Exceptions which occur outside of an Unslicer indicate coding errors or severe protocol violations and cause the connection to be dropped. The exception is logged on the local side with log.err, but the remote end will not be given any reason for the disconnection. Protocol violations are indicated with a BananaError exception.

The Banana object can also choose to respond to Violations by terminating the connection. For example, the .hangupOnLengthViolation flag causes string-too-long violations to be raised directly instead of being handled, which will cause the connection to be dropped (as it occurs in the dataReceived method).

Example

The serialized form of ["foo",(1,2)] is the following token sequence: OPEN STRING(list) STRING(foo) OPEN STRING(tuple) INT(1) INT(2) CLOSE CLOSE. In practice, the STRING(list) would really be something like VOCAB(7), likewise the STRING(tuple) might be VOCAB(8). Here we walk through how this sequence is processed.

The initial Unslicer stack consists of the single RootUnslicer rootun.

OPEN
  rootun.checkToken(OPEN) : must not raise Violation
  enter index phase

VOCAB(7)  (equivalent to STRING(list))
  rootun.openerCheckToken(VOCAB, ()) : must not raise Violation
  VOCAB token is looked up in .incomingVocabulary, turned into "list"
  rootun.doOpen(("list",)) : looks in UnslicerRegistry, returns ListUnslicer
  exit index phase
  the ListUnslicer is pushed on the stack
  listun.start()

STRING(foo)
  listun.checkToken(STRING) : must return None or 3 or greater
  string is assembled
  listun.receiveChild("foo") : appends to list

OPEN
  listun.checkToken(OPEN) : must not raise Violation
  enter index phase

VOCAB(8)  (equivalent to STRING(tuple))
  listun.openerCheckToken(VOCAB, ()) : must not raise Violation
  VOCAB token is looked up, turned into "tuple"
  listun.doOpen(("tuple",)) : delegates through:
                                 BaseUnslicer.open
                                 self.opener (usually the RootUnslicer)
                                 self.opener.open(("tuple",))
                              returns TupleUnslicer
  exit index phase
  TupleUnslicer is pushed on the stack
  tupleun.start()

INT(1)
  tupleun.checkToken(INT) : must not raise Violation
  integer is assembled
  tupleun.receiveChild(1) : appends to list

INT(2)
  tupleun.checkToken(INT) : must not raise Violation
  integer is assembled
  tupleun.receiveChild(2) : appends to list

CLOSE
  tupleun.receiveClose() : creates and returns the tuple (1,2)
                           (could also return a Deferred)
  TupleUnslicer is popped from the stack and discarded
  listun.receiveChild((1,2))

CLOSE
  listun.receiveClose() : creates and returns the list ["foo", (1,2)]
  ListUnslicer is popped from the stack and discarded
  rootun.receiveChild(["foo", (1,2)])

Other Issues

Deferred Object Recreation: The Trouble With Tuples

Types and classes are roughly classified into containers and non-containers. The containers are further divided into mutable and immutable. Some examples of immutable containers are tuples and bound methods. Lists and dicts are mutable containers. Ints and strings are non-containers. Non-containers are always leaf nodes in the object graph.

During unserialization, objects are in one of three states: uncreated, referenceable (but not complete), and complete. Only mutable containers can be referenceable but not complete: immutable containers have no intermediate referenceable state.

Mutable containers (like lists) are referenceable but not complete during traversal of their child nodes. This means those children can reference the list without trouble.

Immutable containers (like tuples) present challenges when unserializing. The object cannot be created until all its components are referenceable. While it is guaranteed that these component objects will be complete before the graph traversal exits the current node, the child nodes are allowed to reference the current node during that traversal. The classic example is the graph created by the following Python fragment:

a = ([],)
a[0].append((a,))

To handle these cases, the TupleUnslicer installs a Deferred into the object table when it begins unserializing (in the .start method). When the tuple is finally complete, the object table is updated and the Deferred is fired with the new tuple.

Containers (both mutable and immutable) are required to pay attention to the types of their incoming children and notice when they receive Deferreds instead of normal objects. These containers are not complete (in the sense described above) until those Deferreds have been replaced with referenceable objects. When the container receives the Deferred, it should attach a callback to it which will perform the replacement. In addition, immutable containers should check after each update to see if all the Deferreds have been cleared, and if so, complete their own object (and fire their own Deferreds so any containers they are a child of may be updated and/or completed).

Security Model

Having the whole Slicer stack particpate in Tasting on the sending side seems to make a lot of sense. It might be better to have a way to push new Taster objects onto a separate stack. This would certainly help with performance, as the common case (where most Slicers ignore .taste) does a pointless method call to every Slice for every object sent. The trick is to make sure that exception cases don't leave a taster stranded on the stack when the object that put it there has gone away.

On the receiving side, each object has a corresponding .taste method, which receives tokens instead of complete objects. This makes sense, because you want to catch the dangerous data before it gets turned into an object, but tokens are a pretty low-level place to do security checks. It might be more useful to have some kind of instance taster stack, with tasters that are asked specifically about (class,state) pairs and whether they should be turned into objects or not.

Because the Unslicers receive their data one token at a time, things like InstanceUnslicer can perform security checks one attribute at a time. traits-style attribute constraints (see the Chaco project or the PyCon-2003 presentation for details) can be implemented by having a per-class dictionary of tests that attribute values must pass before they will be accepted. The instance will only be created if all attributes fit the constraints. The idea is to catch violations before any code is run on the receiving side. Typical checks would be things like .foo must be a number, .bar must not be an instance, .baz must implement the IBazzer interface.

Using the stack instead of a single Taster object means that the rules can be changed depending upon the context of the object being processed. A class that is valid as the first argument to a method call may not be valid as the second argument, or inside a list provided as the first argument. The PBMethodArgumentsUnslicer could change the way its .taste method behaves as its state machine progresses through the argument list.

There are several different ways to implement this Taster stack:

Each object in the Unslicer stack gets to raise an exception if they don't like what they see: unanimous consent is required to let the token or object pass
The top-most unslicer is asked, and it has the option of asking the next slice down. It might not, allowing local I'm sure this is safe classes to override higher-level paranoia.
Unslicer objects may add and remove Taster objects on a separate stack. This is undoubtedly faster but must be done carefully to make sure Tasters and Unslicers stay in sync.

Of course, all this holds true for the sending side as well. A Slicer could enforce a policy that no objects of type Foo will be sent while it is on the stack.

It is anticipated that something like the current Jellyable/Unjellyable classes will be created to offer control over the Slicer/Unslicers used to handle instance of that class.

One eventual goal is to allow PB to implement E-like argument constraints.

Streaming Slices

The big change from the old Jelly scheme is that now serialization/unserialization is done in a more streaming format. Individual tokens are the basic unit of information. The basic tokens are just numbers and strings: anything more complicated (starting at lists) involves composites of other tokens.

The serialization side will be reworked to be a bit more producer-oriented. Objects should be able to defer their serialization temporarily (TODO: really??) like twisted.web resources can do NOT_DONE_YET right now. The big goal here is that large objects which can't fit into the socket buffers should not consume lots of memory, sitting around in a serialized state with nowhere to go. This must be balanced against the confusion caused by time-distributed serialization. PB method calls must retain their current in-order execution, and it must not be possible to interleave serialized state (big mess).

To actually accomplish this, objects should be able to provide their own Slicers. It may be convenient to do this entirely with Adapters, so Banana registers ListSlicer, etc as an ISlicer adapter for the fundamental types; pb.Copyable implements ISlicer by having a method to return a new Slicer; etc.

Likewise on the receiving end, the Unslicer is created when the OPEN token is received, and then receives all the tokens destined for that object.

CBanana, CBananaRun, RunBananaRun

Another goal of the Jelly+Banana->JustBanana change is the hope of writing Slicers and Unslicers in C. The CBanana module should have C objects (structs with function pointers) that can be looked up in a registry table and run to turn python objects into tokens and vice versa. This ought to be faster than running python code to implement the slices, at the cost of less flexibility. It would be nice if the resulting tokens could be sent directly to the socket at the C level without surfacing into python; barring this it is probably a good idea to accumulate the tokens into a large buffer so the code can do a few large writes instead of a gazillion small ones.

It ought to be possible to mix C and Python slices here: if the C code doesn't find the slice in the table, it can fall back to calling a python method that does a lookup in an extensible registry.

Beyond Banana

Random notes and wild speculations: take everything beyond here with two grains of salt

Oldbanana usage

The oldbanana usage model has the layer above banana written in one of two ways. The simple form is to use the banana.encode and banana.decode functions to turn an object into a bytestream. This is used by twisted.spread.publish . The more flexible model is to subclass Banana. The largest example of this technique is, of course, twisted.spread.pb.Broker, but others which use it are twisted.trial.remote and twisted.scripts.conch (which appears to use it over unix-domain sockets).

Banana itself is a Protocol. The Banana subclass would generally override the expressionReceived method, which receives s-expressions (lists of lists). These are processed to figure out what method should be called, etc (processing which only has to deal with strings, numbers, and lists). Then the serialized arguments are sent through Unjelly to produce actual objects.

On output, the subclass usually calls self.sendEncoded with some set of objects. In the case of PB, the arguments to the remote method are turned into s-expressions with jelly, then combined with the method meta-data (object ID, method name, etc), then the whole request is sent to sendEncoded.

Newbanana

Newbanana moves the Jelly functionality into a stack of Banana Slices, and the lowest-level token-to-bytestream conversion into the new Banana object. Instead of overriding expressionReceived, users could push a different root Unslicer. to get more control over the receive process. Currently, Slicers call Banana.sendOpen/sendToken/sendClose/sendAbort, which then creates bytes and does transport.write . To move this into C, the transport should get to call CUnbanana.receiveToken There should be CBananaUnslicers. Probably a parent.addMe(self) instead of banana.stack.append(self), maybe addMeC for the C unslicer. The Banana object is a Protocol, and has a dataReceived method. (maybe in some C form, data could move directly from a CTransport to a CProtocol). It parses tokens and hands them to its Unslicer stack. The root Unslicer is probably created at connectionEstablished time. Subclasses of Banana could use different RootUnslicer objects, or the users might be responsible for setting up the root unslicer. The Banana object is also created with a RootSlicer. Banana.writeToken serializes the token and does transport.write . (a C form could have CSlicer objects which hand tokens to a little CBanana which then hands bytes off to a CTransport). Doing the bytestream-to-Token conversion in C loses a lot of utility when the conversion is done token at a time. It made more sense when a whole mess of s-lists were converted at once. All Slicers currently have a Banana pointer.. maybe they should have a transport pointer instead? The Banana pointer is needed to get to top of the stack. want to be able to unserialize lists/tuples/dicts/strings/ints (basic types) without surfacing into python. want to deliver the completed object to a python function.

Streaming Methods

It would be neat if a method could indicate that it would like to receive its arguments in a streaming fashion. This would involve calling the method early (as soon as the objectID and method name were known), then somehow feeding objects to it as they arrive. The object could return a handler or consumer sub-object which would be fed as tokens arrive over the wire. This consumer should have a way to enforce a constraint on its input.

This consumer object sounds a lot like an Unslicer, so maybe the method schema should indicate that the method will would like to be called right away so it can return an Unslicer to be pushed on the stack. That Unslicer could do whatever it wanted with the incoming tokens, and could enforce constraints with the usual checkToken/doOpen/receiveChild/receiveClose methods.

On the sending side, it would be neat to let a callRemote() invocation provide a Producer or a generator that will supply data as the network buffer becomes available. This could involve pushing a Slicer. Maybe Slicers should be generators.

Common token sequences

Base Python Types

The basic python types are considered safe: the code which is invoked by their receipt is well-understood and there is no way to cause unsafe behavior during unserialization. Resource consumption attacks are mitigated by Constraints imposed by the receiving schema.

Note that the OPEN(dict) slicer is implemented with code that sorts the list of keys before serializing them. It does this to provide deterministic behavior and make testing easier.

IntType, LongType (small+) | INT(value)
IntType, LongType (small-) | NEG(value)
IntType, LongType (large+) | LONGINT(value)
IntType, LongType (large-) | LONGNEG(value)
FloatType | FLOAT(value)
StringType | STRING(value)
StringType (tokenized) | VOCAB(tokennum)
UnicodeType | OPEN(unicode) STRING(str.encode('UTF-8')) CLOSE
ListType | OPEN(list) elem.. CLOSE
TupleType | OPEN(tuple) elem.. CLOSE
DictType, DictionaryType | OPEN(dict) (key,value).. CLOSE
NoneType | OPEN(none) CLOSE
BooleanType | OPEN(boolean) INT(0/1) CLOSE

Extended (unsafe) Python Types

To serialize arbitrary python object graphs (including instances) requires that we allow more types in. This begins to get dangerous: with complex graphs of inter-dependent objects, instances may need to be used (by referencing objects) before they are fully initialized. A schema can be used to make assertions about what object types live where, but in general the contents of those objects are difficult to constrain.

For this reason, these types should only be used in places where you trust the creator of the serialized stream (the same places where you would be willing to use the standard Pickle module). Saving application state to disk and reading it back at startup time is one example.

Extended (unsafe) Python Types
InstanceType | OPEN(instance) STRING(reflect.qual(class)) (attr,value).. CLOSE
ModuleType | OPEN(module) STRING(__name__) CLOSE
ClassType | OPEN(class) STRING(reflect.qual(class)) CLOSE
MethodType | OPEN(method) STRING(__name__) im_self im_class CLOSE
FunctionType | OPEN(function) STRING(module.__name__) CLOSE

PB Sequences

The following sequences are used to support the RPC mechanisms of Perspective Broker.

PB (method call) Sequences
pb.Referenceable | OPEN(remote) INT(ref-id) [InterfaceList] CLOSE
RemoteReference.__del__ | OPEN(decref) INT(refID) CLOSE
pb.Copyable | see InstanceType above
method call | OPEN(call) INT(request-id) INT(obj-id) STRING(methodname) (STRING(argname),argvalue).. CLOSE
method call++ | OPEN(call2) INT(reqID) INT(objID) STRING(interfacename) INT(interfaceversion) STRING(methodname) (STRING(argname),argvalue).. CLOSE (this could be folded into 'call' with only 2 bytes of overhead)
method response (success) | OPEN(answer) INT(request-id) value CLOSE
method response (exception) | OPEN(error) INT(request-id) value CLOSE

The first time a pb.Referenceable is sent, the second object is an InterfaceList, which is a list of tuples of (interfacename, versionnum), and therefore constrainable by a schema of ListOf(TupleOf(str,int)) with some appropriate maximum-length restrictions. This InterfaceList describes all the Interfaces that the corresponding pb.Referenceable implements. The receiver uses this list to look up local Interfaces (and therefore Schemas) to attach to the pb.RemoteReference. This is how method schemas are checked on the sender side.

This implies that Interfaces must be registered, just as classes are for pb.Copyable. TODO: what happens if an unknown Interface is received? TODO: are multiple versions of the same interface allowed? If so, how is that specified?

Unhandled types

The following types are not handled by any slicer, and will raise a KeyError if one is referenced by an object being sliced. This technically imposes a limit upon the kinds of objects that can be serialized, even by a unsafe serializer, but in practice it is not really an issue, as many of these objects have no meaning outside the program invocation which created them.

- types that might be nice to have
ComplexType
SliceType
TypeType
XRangeType
- types that aren't really that useful
BufferType
BuiltinFunctionType
BuiltinMethodType
CodeType
DictProxyType
EllipsisType
NotImplementedType
UnboundMethodType
- types that are meaningless outside the creator
TracebackType
FileType
FrameType
GeneratorType
LambdaType

Unhandled (but don't worry about it) types

ObjectType is the root class of all other types. All objects are known by some other type in addition to ObjectType, so the fact that it is not handled explicitly does not matter.

StringTypes is simply a list of StringType and UnicodeType, so it does not need to be explicitly handled either.

Internal types

The following sequences are internal.

The OPEN(vocab) sequence is used to update the forward compression token-to-string table used by the VOCAB token. It is followed by a series of number/string pairs. All numbers that appear in VOCAB tokens must be associated with a string by appearing in the most recent OPEN(vocab) sequence.

internal types
vocab dict | OPEN(vocab) (num,string).. CLOSE

NewPB

This document describes the new PB protocol. This is a layer on top of Banana which provides remote object access (method invocation and instance transfer).

Fundamentally, PB is about one side keeping a RemoteReference to the other side's Referenceable. The Referenceable has some methods that can be invoked remotely: functionality it is offering to remote callers. Those callers hold RemoteReferences which point to it. The RemoteReference object offers a way to invoke those methods (generally through the callRemote method).

There are plenty of other details, starting with how the RemoteReference is obtained, and how arguments and return values are communicated.

For the purposes of this document, we will designate the side that holds the actual Referenceable object as local, and the side that holds the proxy RemoteReference object as remote. This distinction is only meaningful with respect to a single RemoteReference/Referenceable pair. One program may hold Referenceable A and RemoteReference B, paired with another that holds RemoteReference A and Referenceable B. Once initialization is complete, PB is a symmetric protocol.

It is helpful to think of PB as providing a wire or pipe that connects two programs. Objects are put into this pipe at one end, and something related to the object comes out the other end. These two objects are said to correspond to each other. Basic types (like lists and dictionaries) are handled by Banana, but more complex types (like instances) are treated specially, so that most of the time there is a native form (as present on the local side) that goes into the pipe, and a remote form that comes out.

Initialization

The PB session begins with some feature negotiation and (generally) the receipt of a VocabularyDict. Usually this takes place over an interactive transport, like a TCP connection, but newpb can also be used in a more batched message-oriented mode, as long as both the creator of the method call request and its eventual consumer are in agreement about their shared state (at least, this is the intention.. there are still pieces that need to be implemented to make this possible).

The local side keeps a table which provides a bidirectional mapping between Referenceable objects and a connection-local object-ID number. This table begins with a single object called the Root, which is implicitly given ID number 0. Everything else is bootstrapped through this object. For the typical PB Broker, this root object performs cred authentication and returns other Referenceables as the cred Avatar.

The remote side has a collection of RemoteReference objects, each of which knows the object-ID of the corresponding Referenceable, as well as the Broker which provides the connection to the other Broker. The remote side must do reference-tracking of these RemoteReferences, because as long as it remains alive, the local-side Broker must maintain a reference to the original Referenceable.

Method Calls

The remote side invokes a remote method by calling ref.callRemote() on its RemoteReference. This starts by validating the method name and arguments against a Schema (described below). It then creates a new Request object which will live until the method call has either completed successfully or failed due to an exception (including the connection being lost).

It then sends a call banana sequence over the wire. This sequence indicates the request ID (used to match the request with the resulting answer or error response), the object ID of the Referenceable being targeted, a string to indicate the name of the method being invoked, and the arguments to be passed into the method.

All arguments are passed by name (i.e. keyword arguments instead of positional parameters). Each argument is subject to the argument transformation described below.

The local side receives the call sequence, uses the object-ID to look up the Referenceable, finds the desired method, then applies the method's schema to the incoming arguments. If they are acceptable, it invokes the method. A normal return value it sent back immediately in an answer sequence. If the method returns a Deferred, the answer will be sent back when the Deferred fires. If the method raises an exception (or the Deferred does an errback), the resulting Failure is sent back in a error sequence. Both the answer and the error start with the request-ID so they can be used to complete the Request object waiting on the remote side.

Argument Transformation

To understand this section, it may be useful to review the Banana documentation on serializing object graphs. Also note that method arguments and method return values are handled identically.

Basic types (lists, tuples, dictionaries) are serialized and unserialized as you would expect: the resulting object would (if it existed in the sender's address space) compare as equal (but of course not identical, because the objects will exist at different memory locations).

Shared References, Serialization Scope

Shared references to the same object are handled correctly. Banana is responsible for noticing that a sharable object has been serialized before (or at least has begun serialization) and inserts reference markers so that the object graph can be reconstructed. This introduces the concept of serialization scope: the boundaries beyond which shared references are not maintained.

For PB, serialization is scoped to the method call. If an object is referenced by two arguments to the same method call, that method will see two references to the same object. If those arguments are containers of some form, which (eventually) hold a reference to the same object, the object graph will be preserved. For example:

class Caller:
    def start(self):
        obj = [1, 2, 3]
        self.remote.callRemote("both", obj, obj)
        self.remote.callRemote("deeper", ["a", obj], (4, 5, obj))

class Called(pb.Referenceable):
    def remote_both(self, arg1, arg2):
        assert arg1 is arg2
        assert arg1 == [1,2,3]
    def remote_deeper(self, listarg, tuplearg):
        ref1 = listarg[1]
        ref2 = tuplearg[2]
        assert ref1 is ref2
        assert ref1 == [1,2,3]

But if the remote-side object is referenced in two distinct remote method invocations, the local-side methods will see two separate objects. For example:

class Caller:
    def start(self):
        self.obj = [1, 2, 3]
        d = self.remote.callRemote("one", self.obj)
        d.addCallback(self.next)
    def next(self, res):
        self.remote.callRemote("two", self.obj)

class Called(pb.Referenceable):
    def remote_one(self, ref1):
        assert ref1 == [1,2,3]
        self.ref1 = ref1

    def remote_two(self, ref2):
        assert ref2 == [1,2,3]
        assert ref1 is not ref2 # not the same object

You can think of the method call itself being a node in the object graph, with the method arguments as its children. The method call node is picked up and the resulting sub-tree is serialized with no knowledge of anything outside the sub-treeThis isn't quite true: for some objects, serialization is scoped to the connection as a whole. Referenceables and RemoteReferences are like this..

The value returned by a method call is serialized by itself, without reference to the arguments that were given to the method. If a remote method is called with a list, and the method returns its argument unchanged, the caller will get back a deep copy of the list it passed in.

Referenceables, RemoteReferences

Referenceables are transformed into RemoteReferences when they are sent over the wire. As one side traverses the object graph of the method arguments (or the return value), each Referenceable object it encounters it serialized with a remote sequence, that includes the object-ID number. When the other side is unserializing the token stream, it creates a RemoteReference object (TODO: or uses one that already exists).

Likewise, if an argument (or return value) contains a RemoteReference, and it is being sent back to the Broker that holds the original Referenceable then it will be turned back into that Referenceable when it arrives. In this case, the caller of a remote method which returns its argument unchanged will see a a result that is identical to what it passed in:

class Target(pb.Referenceable):
    pass

class Caller:
    def start(self):
        self.obj = Target()
        d = self.remote.callRemote("echo", self.obj)
        d.addCallback(self.next)
    def next(self, res):
        assert res is self.obj

class Called(pb.Referenceable):
    def remote_echo(self, arg):
        # arg is a RemoteReference to a Target() instance 
        return arg

In the future, there may be other classes which behave this way. In particular, Referenceable and Callable may be distinct qualities.

Copyable, RemoteCopy

Some objects can be marked to indicate that they should be copied bodily each time they traverse the wire. Classes which inherit from pb.Copyable are passed-by-value. Their getTypeToCopy and getStateToCopy methods are used to assemble the data that will be serialized.

The receiving side must register a RemoteCopy subclass under the same name as returned by the sender's getTypeToCopy value.

Slicers, ISlicer

Each object gets Sliced as it goes over the wire: Referenceable and Copyable are merely special cases. They have Slicers which implement specific behaviors when they appear before the serialization process. You can implement your own Slicers to do other things.

Arbitrary Instances are NOT serialized

Arbitrary instances (that is, anything which does not have an ISlicer adapter) are not serialized. If an argument to a remote method contains one, you will get a Violation exception when you attempt to serialize it (i.e., the Deferred that you get from callRemote will errback with a Failure that contains a Violation exception). If the return value contains one, the Violation will be logged on the local side, and the remote caller will see an error just as if your method had raised a Violation itself.

There are two reasons for this. The first is a security precaution: you must explicitly mark the classes that are willing to reveal their contents to the world. This reduces the chance of leaking sensitive information.

The second is because it is not actually meaningful to send the contents of an arbitrary object. The recipient only gets the class name and a dictionary with the object's state. Which class should it use to create the corresponding object? It could attempt to import one based upon the classname (the approach pickle uses), but that would give a remote attacker unrestricted access to classes which could do absolutely anything: very dangerous.

Both ends must be willing to transport the object. The sending side expresses this by marking the class (subclassing Copyable, or registering an ISlicer adapter). The receiving side must register the class as well (TODO: how?).

PB Sequences

There are several Banana sequences which are used to support the RPC mechanisms of Perspective Broker. These are in addition to the usual ones listed in the Banana docs.

Top-Level Sequences

These sequences only appear at the top-level (never inside another object).

PB (method call) Sequences
method call | OPEN(call) INT(request-id) INT/STR(your-reference-id) STRING(methodname) (STRING(argname),argvalue).. CLOSE
method call++ | OPEN(call2) INT(request-id) INT/STR(your-reference-id) STRING(interfacename) STRING(methodname) (STRING(argname),argvalue).. CLOSE (this could be folded into 'call' with only 2 bytes of overhead)
method response (success) | OPEN(answer) INT(request-id) value CLOSE
method response (exception) | OPEN(error) INT(request-id) value CLOSE
RemoteReference.__del__ | OPEN(decref) INT(your-reference-id) CLOSE

Internal Sequences

The following sequences are used to serialize PB-specific objects. They never appear at the top-level, but only as the argument value or return value (or somewhere inside them).

PB (method call) Sequences
pb.Referenceable | OPEN(my-reference) INT(clid) [OPEN(list) InterfaceList.. CLOSE] CLOSE
pb.RemoteReference | OPEN(your-reference) INT(clid) CLOSE
pb.Copyable | OPEN(copyable) STRING(reflect.qual(class)) (attr,value).. CLOSE

The first time a pb.Referenceable is sent, the second object is an InterfaceList, which is a list of interfacename strings, and therefore constrainable by a schema of ListOf(str) with some appropriate maximum-length restrictions. This InterfaceList describes all the Interfaces that the corresponding pb.Referenceable implements. The receiver uses this list to look up local Interfaces (and therefore Schemas) to attach to the pb.RemoteReference. This is how method schemas are checked on the sender side.

This implies that Interfaces must be registered, just as classes are for pb.Copyable. TODO: what happens if an unknown Interface is received?

Classes which wish to be passed by value should either inherit from pb.Copyable or have an ICopyable adapter registered for them. On the receiving side, the registerRemoteCopy function must be used to register a factory, which can be a pb.RemoteCopy subclass or something else which implements IRemoteCopy.

Implementation notes

Outgoing Referenceables

The side which holds the Referenceable uses a ReferenceableSlicer to serialize it. Each Referenceable is tracked with a process-Unique ID (abbreviated puid). As the name implies, this number refers to a specific object within a given process: it is scoped to the process (and is never sent to another process), but it spans multiple PB connections (any given object will have the same puid regardless of which connection is referring to it). The puid is an integer, normally obtained with id(obj), but you can override the object's processUniqueID method to use something else (this might be useful for objects that are really proxies for something else). Any two objects with the same puid are serialized identically.

All Referenceables sent over the wire (as arguments or return values for remote methods) are given a connection-local ID (clid) which is scoped to one end of the connection. The Referenceable is serialized with this number, using a banana sequence of OPEN "my-reference" clid. The remote peer (the side that holds the RemoteReference) knows the Referenceable by the clid sent to represent it. These are small integers. From a security point of view, any object sent across the wire (and thus given a clid) is forever accessible to the remote end (or at least until the connection is dropped).

The sending side uses the Broker.clids dict to map puid to clid. It uses the Broker.localObjects dict to map clid to Referenceable. The reference from .localObjects also has the side-effect of making sure the Referenceable doesn't go out of scope while the remote end holds a reference.

Broker.currentLocalID is used as a counter to create clid values.

RemoteReference

In response to the incoming my-reference sequence, the receiving side creates a RemoteReference that remembers its Broker and the clid value. The RemoteReference is stashed in the Broker.remoteReferences weakref dictionary (which maps from clid to RemoteReference), to make sure that a single Referenceable is always turned into the same RemoteReference. Note that this is not infallible: if the recipient forgets about the RemoteReference, PB will too. But if they really do forget about it, then they won't be able to tell that the replacement is not the same as the originalunless they do something crazy like remembering the id(obj) of the old object and check to see if it is the same as that of the new one. But id(obj) is only unique among live objects anyway. It will have a different clid.

This RemoteReference is where the .callRemote method lives. When used to invoke remote methods, the clid is used as the second token of a call sequence. In this context, the clid is a your-reference: it refers to the recipient's .localObjects table. The Referenceable-holder's my-reference-id is sent back to them as the your-reference-id argument of the call sequence.

The RemoteReference isn't always used to invoke remote methods: it could appear in an argument or a return value instead: the goal is to have the Referenceable-holder see their same Referenceable come back to them. In this case, the clid is put as the first token of a your-reference sequence. The Referenceable-holder looks up the clid in their .localObjects table and puts the result in the method argument or return value.

URL References

In addition to the implicitly-created numerically-indexed Referenceable instances (kept in the Broker's .localObjects dict), there are explicitly-registered string-indexed Referenceables kept in the PBServerFactory's localObjects dictionary. This table is used to publish objects to the outside world. These objects are the targets of the pb.callRemoteURL function.

To access these, a RemoteReference must be created that refers to a string clid instead of a numeric one. This RemoteReference is created manually, rather than being generated automatically upon the receipt of a my-reference sequence. The pb.callRemoteURL is responsible for this. It also assumes a list of Interface names (which are usually provided by the holder of the Referenceable).

To invoke methods on a URL-indexed object, a string token is used as the clid in the your-reference-id argument of a call sequence.

At present, the clid of a your-reference sequence must be numeric: URL-indexed objects may not be used in arguments or return values of method invocations. If the URL-indexed object returns self from the method, the caller will get a regular numeric (implicit) reference. This may change in the future as the URL-based referencing scheme is developed. It might also become possible for string clids to appear in my-reference sequences, giving Referenceable-holders the ability to publish URL references explicitly.

It might also become possible to have these URLs point to other servers. In this case, a remote sequence will probably be used, rather than the my-reference sequence used for implicit references.

Note that these URL-endpoints are per-Factory, so they are shared between multiple connections (the implicitly-created references are only available on the connection that created them). The PBServerFactory is created with a root object, which is a URL-endpoint with a clid of an empty string.

NewPB Schemas

NOTE! This is all preliminary and is more an exercise in semiconscious protocol design than anything else. Do not believe this document. This sentence is lying. So there.

"""

RemoteReference objects should all be tagged with interfaces that they
implement, which point to representations of the method schemas.  When a remote
method is called, PB should look up the appropriate method and serialize the
argument list accordingly.

We plan to eliminate positional arguments, so local RemoteReferences use their
schema to convert callRemote calls with positional arguments to all-keyword
arguments before serialization.

Conversion to the appropriate version interface should be handled at the
application level.  Eventually, with careful use of twisted.python.context, we
might be able to provide automated tools for helping application authors
automatically convert interface calls and isolate version-conversion code, but
that is probably pretty hard.

"""


class Attributes:
    def __init__(self,*a,**k):
        pass

X = Attributes(
    ('hello', str),
    ('goodbye', int),
    ('next', Shared(Narf)),             # allow the possibility of multiple or circular references
                                        # the default is to make multiple copies
                                        # to avoid making the serializer do extra work
    ('asdf', ListOf(Narf, maxLength=30)),
    ('fdsa', (Narf, String(maxLength=5), int)),
    ('qqqq', DictOf(str, Narf, maxKeys=30)),
    ('larg', AttributeDict(('A', int),
                           ('X', Number),
                           ('Z', float))),
    Optional("foo", str),
    Optional("bar", str, default=None),
    ignoreUnknown=True,
    )

X = Attributes(
    attributes={ 'hello': str,     # this form doesn't allow Optional()
                 'goodbye': int,
               },
    Optional("foo", str),  # but both can be used at once
    ignoreUnknown=True)

class Narf(Remoteable):
    # step 1
    __schema__ = X
    # step 2 (possibly - this loses information)
    class schema:
        hello = str
        goodbye = int
        class add:
            x = Number
            y = Number
            __return__ = Copy(Number)

        class getRemoteThingy:
            fooID = Arg(WhateverID, default=None)
            barID = Arg(WhateverID, default=None)
            __return__ = Reference(Narf)

    # step 3 - this is the only example that shows argument order, which we
    # _do_ need in order to translate positional arguments to callRemote, so
    # don't take the nested-classes example too seriously.

    schema = """
    int add (int a, int b)
    """

    # Since the above schema could also be used for Formless, or possibly for
    # World (for state) we can also do:

    class remote_schema:
        """blah blah
        """

    # You could even subclass that from the other one...

    class remote_schema(schema):
        dontUse = 'hello', 'goodbye'

            
    def remote_add(self, x, y):
        return x + y

    def rejuvinate(self, deadPlayer):
        return Reference(deadPlayer.bringToLife())

    # "Remoteable" is a new concept - objects which may be method-published
    # remotely _or_ copied remotely.  The schema objects support both method /
    # interface definitions and state definitions, so which one gets used can
    # be defined by the sending side as to whether it sends a
    # Copy(theRemoteable) or Reference(theRemoteable)

    # (also, with methods that are explicitly published by a schema there is no
    # longer technically any security need for the remote_ prefix, which, based
    # on past experience can be kind of annoying if you want to provide the
    # same methods locally and remotely)

    # outstanding design choice - Referenceable and Copyable are subclasses of
    # Remoteable, but should they restrict the possibility of sending it the
    # other way or 

    def getPlayerInfo(self, playerID):
        return CopyOf(self.players[playerID])

    def getRemoteThingy(self, fooID, barID):
        return ReferenceTo(self.players[selfPlayerID])


class RemoteNarf(Remoted):
    __schema__ = X
    # or, example of a difference between local and remote
    class schema:
        class getRemoteThingy:
            __return__ = Reference(RemoteNarf)
        class movementUpdate:
            posX = int
            posY = int
            __return__ = None           # No return value
            __wait__ = False            # Don't wait for the answer
            __reliable__ = False        # Feel free to send this over UDP
            __ordered__ = True          # but send in order!
            __priority__ = 3            # use priority queue / stream 3
            __failure__ = FullFailure   # allow full serialization of failures
            __failure__ = ErrorMessage  # default: trivial failures, or str or int

            # These options may imply different method names - e.g. '__wait__ =
            # False' might imply that you can't use callRemote, you have to
            # call 'sendRemote' instead... __reliable__ = False might be
            # 'callRemoteUnreliable' (longer method name to make it less
            # convenient to call by accident...)


## (and yes, donovan, we know that TypedInterface exists and we are going to
## use it.  we're just screwing around with other syntaxes to see what about PB
## might be different.)

Common banana sequences:

A reference to a remote object.
   (On the sending side: Referenceable or ReferenceTo(aRemoteable)
    On the receiving side: RemoteReference)
('remote', reference-id, interface, version, interface, version, ...)


A call to a remote method:
('fastcall', request-id, reference-id, method-name, 'arg-name', arg1, 'arg-name', arg2)

A call to a remote method with extra spicy metadata:
('call', request-id, reference-id, interface, version, method-name, 'arg-name', arg1, 'arg-name', arg2)

Special hack: request-id of 0 means 'do not answer this call, do not acknowledge', etc.

Answer to a method call:
('answer', request-id, response)
('error', request-id, response)

Decrement a reference incremented by 'remote' command:
('decref', reference-id)

Broker currently has 9 proto_ methods:

_version(vnum): accept a version number, compare to ours, reject if different

_didNotUnderstand(command): log command, maybe drop connection

_message(reqID, objID, message, answerRequired, netArgs, netKw):
_cachemessage (like _message but finds objID with self.cachedLocallyAs instead
               of self.localObjectForID, used by RemoteCacheMethod and
               RemoteCacheObserver)
 look up objID, invoke it with .remoteMessageReceived(message, args),
 send "answer"(reqID, results)

_answer(reqID, results): look up self.waitingForAnswers[reqID] and fire
                         callback with results

_error(reqID, failure): lookup waitingForAnswers, fire errback

_decref(objID): dec refcount of self.localObjects[objID]. Sent in
                RemoteReference.__del__

_decache(objID): dec refcount of self.remotelyCachedObjects[objID]

_uncache(objID): remove obj from self.locallyCachedObjects[objID]

stuff

A RemoteReference/RemoteCopy (called a Remote for now) has a schema attached to it. remote.callRemote(methodname, *args) does schema.getMethodSchema(methodname) to obtain a MethodConstraint that describes the individual method. This MethodConstraint (or MethodSchema) has other attributes which are used by either end: what arguments are allowed and/or expected, calling conventions (synchronous, in-order, priority, etc), and how the return value should be constrained.

To use the Remote like a RemoteCopy ...

Remote:
 .methods
 .attributes
 .getMethodSchema(methodname) -> MethodConstraint
 .getAttributeSchema(attrname) -> a Constraint

XPCOM idl specifies methods and attributes (readonly, readwrite). A Remote
object which represented a distant XPCOM object would have a Schema that is
created by parsing the IDL. Its callRemote would do the appropriate
marshalling. Issue1: XPCOM lets methods have in/out/inout parameters.. these
must be detected and a wrapper generated. Issue2: what about attribute
set/get operations? Could add setRemote and getRemote for these.

---

Some of the schema questions come down to how PBRootSlicer should deal with
instances. The question is whether to treat the instance as a Referenceable
(copy-by-reference: create and transmit a reference number, which will be
turned into a RemoteReference on the other end), or as a Copyable
(copy-by-value: collect some instance state and send it as an instance).
This decision could be made by looking at what the instance inherits from:

  if isinstance(obj, pb.Referenceable):
      sendByReference(obj)
  elif isinstance(obj, pb.Copyable):
      sendByValue(obj)
  else:
      raise InsecureJellyError

or by what it can be adapted to:

  r = IReferenceable(obj, None)
  if r:
      sendByReference(r)
  else:
      r = ICopyable(obj, None)
      if r:
          sendByValue(r)
      else:
          raise InsecureJellyError

The decision could also be influenced by the sending schema currently in
effect. Side A invokes a method on side B. A knows of a schema which states
that the 'foo' argument of this method should be a CopyableSpam, so it
requires the object be adaptable to ICopyableSpam (which is then copied by
value) tries to comply when that argument is serialized. B will enforce its
own schema. When B returns a result to A, the method-result schema on B's
side can influence how the return value is handled.

For bonus points, it may be possible to send the object as a combination of
these two. That may get pretty hard to follow, though.

adapters and Referenceable/Copyable

One possibility: rather than using a SlicerRegistry, use Adapters. The ISliceable interface has one method: getSlicer(). Slicer.py would register adapters for basic types (list, dict, etc) that would just return an appropriate ListSlicer, etc. Instances which would have been pb.Copyable subclasses in oldpb can still inherit from pb.Copyable, which now implements ISliceable and produces a Slicer (opentype='instance') that calls getStateToCopy() (although the subclass-__implements__ handling is now more important than before). pb.Referenceable implements ISlicer and produces a Slicer (opentype='reference'?) which (possibly) registers itself in the broker and then sends the reference number (along with a schema if necessary (and the other end wants them)).

Classes are also welcome to implement ISlicer themselves and produce whatever clever (streaming?) Slicer objects they like.

On the receiving side, we still need a registry to provide reasonable security. There are two registries. The first is the RootUnslicer.openRegistry, and maps OPEN types to Unslicer factories. It is used in doOpen().

The second registry should map opentype=instance class names to something which can handle the instance contents. Should this be a replacement Unslicer?